CHAPTER 3

Portuguese Slave Trade from the
Tamil Coast to Goa and Cochin in
India and to Melaka and Aceh in
South East Asia, 1547-1625

According to available Tamil sources, Slaves were never exported overseas according to available ancient and medieval sources though humans were purchased and sold like goods in the inland of Tamil country. There was non-governmental trade of export of slaves and also by private individuals. Marco Polo the medieval traveller noted that slaves were exported from the ports of Bengal.1 This fact had been also affirmed by the Duarte Barbosa the Portuguese traveller in the early sixteenth century.2

THE KINGS OF PORTUGAL IN LISBON, THE
VICEROYS IN GOA AND THE REGULATIONS
ISSUED ON SLAVERY AND SLAVE TRADE

Vasco da Gama arrived at Calicut on the western coast of India in 1498 and later the Portuguese began to expand their commercial operations on the Tamil coast. Enslavement and slave trade commenced when the Portuguese settled in the coastal fringes. Lourenço Moreno and Diogo Pereira wrote in 1510 to the king of Portugal in Lisbon concerning the slavery that was getting in the way of larger services to God and king. They mentioned that the ship captains in India were unwilling to carry sick and crippled men while in the service of the king, they would rather bring their ships full of slaves, which was an act of great inhumanity; and, if they brought some sick men it was because they were bribed. Hence they requested the king to offer a solution to this situation.3 Thus it is learnt that slaves from India were shipped to Portugal.

Slaves and slave trade were among the issues targeted by a set of Portuguese laws enacted in 1520 known as Ordenações da Índia. A royal provision enacted in November 1521 confirmed that, despite not being included in the Ordenações Manuelinas, this code was to be enforced in Portuguese trading settlements. It gave official recognition to the enslavement of Muslims in the Indian Ocean. This was the law that confirmed the project of Portuguese royal monopoly on spices in the Indian Ocean. In this provision, any person, including officials of the Portuguese colonial administration, Christians, Muslims, and people from any other nation were forbidden to trade pepper, clover, ginger, cinnamon, mace, nutmeg, lacquer, silk and the mineral tincal.

A letter was therefore sent to Diogo Lopes de Sequeira, the governor in Goa in March 1520, where the king explained in detail the reasons for this move. According to the letter, the presence of slaves on ships coming from India was a waste of supplies, among other inconveniences. For that reason, the king restricted the presence of slaves on board of the said vessels, although he admitted that private merchants in the service of the king were not to follow the said restriction, in respect to contracts they had with other merchants. However, in the letter, the king provided that, if it was necessary for the safety of the ship, the king would allow up to 20 slaves or even more if necessary, to come on board, as long as they were men. The reason for this no-female restriction had nothing to do with social norms. The letter explained, men were allowed as long as they were able and knowledgeable enough to help in sailing the ship.4

The pepper and spice trade had restrictions in regard to trading officials and the commerce between Portuguese ports, but the slave trade was simply unregulated in India. Human trafficking became one choice for the small traders who were in search of profit but lacked enough capital to take part in the spice trade. The result was an active slave trade. The Portuguese legislation in this period was directed at regulating and curtailing slave trading practices, not defining legitimacy or restricting ownership of slaves. Slave trade was free, unless it represented any danger to the spice trade.

The king of Portugal received complaints regarding the Portuguese who were not freeing their baptized slaves as they should. Hence the king wrote a letter to Dom Henrique de Menezes, the Governor of Goa (1524-6) and instructed him on how to proceed in such cases, confirming that slaves were to be freed upon baptism. The same matter had been repeated again in 1533, when the king wrote to Governor D. Nuno da Cunha.5 In 1556 before passing away, Dom João III, the king of Portugal reversed his decision and ruled that baptized slaves owned by Muslims or Hindus should be sold to Christians, but not be freed. These slaves were to be kept as slaves by their new masters.6 The only and real obligation was that converted slaves had to be sold only to Christians.

Dom Sebastiao, the new king of Portugal (1557-78) wrote to Francisco Barreto, the Governor in Goa, that slaves owned by Muslims were to be sold to Christians upon baptism, but not regain their freedom.7 The King of Portugal also gave instructions to the departing new Viceroy Dom Luís de Ataíde in 1568, in which he declared that Muslims illegally transporting pepper outside of the Malabar Coast could be captured and enslaved. He indicated specifically that they were to be considered as slaves being captives of just war.8

Dom Constantino de Bragança, the Portuguese viceroy of India (1558-61) ruled that slaves owned by Hindus should be freed upon baptism. The converted slaves brought by Hindus to be sold should then be auctioned, and after being purchased by Christians, the amount had to be delivered to its former owner. At the same time, the viceroy forbade Hindus to buy Christian slaves in the Portuguese trading settlements.9 Mathias de Albuquerque the viceroy in Goa in 1590s ruled that baptized slaves should not be owned by Hindus.10 Thus various regulations were enforced on slaves and slavery in India because of the tension that had developed between baptism of slaves and manumission of slaves.

THE PURCHASE SLAVES FROM THE TAMIL
COAST BY THE PORTUGUESE TRADERS

Portuguese traders had settled on the Tamil coast since 1507. They purchased slaves and employed them in domestic work in their trading settlements. Thus, over a period of time a large population of slaves lived in the Portuguese settlements.11 Slaves were not allowed to be transported overseas in ships owing to a ban issued on the export of slaves by the local nayaka rulers of Vijayanagar empire. Portuguese traders later purchased slaves from the Tamil Coast and sold them to fellow settlers in Goa and Cochin. These purchased the slaves were employed by the masters for various purposes.

A TAMIL SLAVE IN GOA, 1548

In a testament dated 2 June 1548 by Antonio de Faria e Sousa, a rich merchant at the time of his death in Goa confided that he owned 30 slaves. One finds one Tamil male slave besides 12 Chinese slaves, two from the island of Java, two from Pegu, one from Japan, one from Gujarat, one from Makassar and one from Sri Lanka. It is found that 64 per cent of these slaves of Faria were males and 36 per cent were females, while 77 per cent were adults and 23 per cent were children.12 This record suggests that Portuguese merchants had extensive slave trading networks in Asia.

THE ESCAPE OF A TAMIL SLAVE
IN COCHIN, 1558

Another Portuguese trader called Luis Rodrigues lived at Cochin. He had also built an extensive commercial network from Cochin to Bengal and Kedah. He also owned several ships that sailed from Melaka to China during the period of 1545 and 1558 and he invested funds in the purchase of Chinese commodities. He had residences in the city of Cochin and Melaka too. Luis Rodrigues owned a Tamil male slave by name Duarte and he ran away because the master had ill-treated him. It is known that Rodrigues had many slaves called Antonio, Joana and Isabel who were employed. Peter the slave was mainly employed to seal the joints of sailing vessels with oakum.13

THE SLAVERY AND SLAVE TRADE ON THE
TAMIL COAST AND THE JESUIT
MISSIONARIES, 1545-1552

Miguel Vaz the Jesuit wrote to Dom João III, the king of Portugal in 1545 and he gave details regarding the deeds of Portuguese merchants who brought slaves from the Coromandel Coast to Goa. He said that after the arrival of slaves in Goa they were resold as human cargo. The Jesuit Provincial was mainly concerned with the fate of these men and women slaves. He suggested that, rather than passing on the slaves to Muslim masters, under Portuguese dominance the slaves should be converted to Christianity, without offering any resistance.14

Henrique Henriques the Jesuit at Vembar on the Pearl Fishery Coast recorded a case of a slave in 1548 which was narrated to him by a slave himself. The slave was raised in the Santa Fé College of Goa and he wished to accompany the missionaries on their trip to the Moluccas and he secretly boarded the ship. After he was discovered as a stowaway passenger he was taken off the sailing vessel in Cochin and left with a Portuguese man who was asked to bring the slave back to Goa. The slave thereafter ran away and ended up in the hands of Muslim traders who tried to convert him. Rescued by a Portuguese captain, the slave told not only his own tale of resistance, but also those of many other fugitive slaves under the Muslims. Henriques through this communication illustrated the need for the missionaries to work among the slaves. Henriques also mentioned at that time that many slaves had asked Francis Xavier to intervene in their favour, in order to allow them to become Christians and to be freed. Xavier had promised them that he would try his best, but no further information had been found in his letter.15

Nicolao Lancillotto the Jesuit had written a letter to Ignatius Loyola in 1550 wherein he elaborated the details on the legal aspects slavery in Tamil country. One finds that the missionary had denounced Portuguese soldiers who after settling in the Tamil Coast enslaved the natives. They also baptized their slaves, without any liturgical concern. These practices, Lancillotto said had paved the way to a lack of rigour towards the local Christian community that the Jesuits were planning to correct. The missionary attributed to these forceful baptisms the general situation of Tamil Christians, who received the baptism for reasons considered by the missionary to be unholy or secular.16

Lancillotto gave a detailed account on the ways how an individual became a slave in India. At first he referred to the political power the local rulers had over the populace, a dominion that included the capacity to sell subjects as slaves.17 Next he said that any individual could sell a person or relative over whom he or she had any power. He added that parents sold their children, uncles and aunts sold their nephews and nieces and the older brothers sold younger siblings. He also mentioned that there was the problem of volunteer slavery, which according to Lancillotto accounted for thousands becoming new slaves every day in Tamil country.

The missionary reiterated that all these various types of slaves were traded as merchandise, like horses and cattle in Europe. His concerns were mainly two. The first was whether the Jesuits were allowed to buy these types of slaves and, second, if it was licit to speculate on their prices. He stated that one could buy three slaves when prices were low, but should the buyer repay the seller the difference when the market changed and prices went up later on.18

Ignatius Loyola replied to this letter including four other earlier letters sent by Lancillotto in a single short letter dated 27 January 1552. Ignatius did not offer any concrete answer to the questioning on legitimacy of slavery. Perhaps he preferred to leave the matter to be decided by those who lived on the Tamil Coast. May be he felt that the issue could be decided locally by people who had a better understanding of the situation.19

THE DISCUSSION OF MISSIONARIES ON SLAVERY
AND SLAVES AT THE FIRST PROVINCIAL
COUNCIL IN GOA, 1567

The legitimacy of enslavement and the issue that remained unanswered for long, finally came for discussion before the ecclesiastical authorities in Goa. The missionaries deliberated the matter in the Synod of 1567 and thus came the striking blow on the unruly slave market of the Portuguese in India. It triggered a series of legal acts by the crown in order to control and curtail slavery in the name of Christian conversions and the mission. The Goa decrees are divided into four parts or Acts, in the following order: Profession of faith and presentation; conversion of the infidels and new-converts; reform of the Church and Reform of the Muslims. Enslavement and related practices were spread throughout the decrees. The text refers to young children and slaves, as a single legal entity. It explained how political power and dominance was to be organized in the colonial societies. Missionaries were central for the most basic organizational unity of a society, the family. They had power over members of their group, but especially over their children. This relationship is recreated between the master and his or her slave. The master (dominus) assumes control (dominium) over his slave.20 The most basic notion of dominance over a slave comes from the Roman law of nations, that had been used to explain that the winning party in a just war had the right to kill subjugated enemies. The winner could also choose, instead, a less drastic punishment, by enslaving the defeated.21

The council of 1567 vide its decree 16 mentioned that non-Christians should not possess a Christian slave. If they happened to buy or sell one, such a slave would be considered free. It stated that the same would apply to any slave of non-Christian master on becoming Christian, who would not receive any price for him or her. If the slave was brought for sale, they should not be paid more than 12 cruzados, and this would be applicable only if the slave was sold within three months after entering the Portuguese territory. Beyond this time limit the slave would be considered free. As regards slaves, who might belong to the jurisdiction of allies, to be baptized, the mutual accord had to be respected, namely, if the allies returned slaves to the Portuguese or paid for them, the Portuguese also had to respond in the same manner.22

JESUIT LETTERS AND REPORTS ON
SLAVERY AND SLAVES, 1571-1576

A report of 1571 has mentioned that many Portuguese had 15 to 50 female slaves each. Masters and even servants and male slaves slept with them.23 A letter was written in 1576 to Mercurian the Jesuit Superior-General in Rome, that in India even poor native Christians had their slaves and that it was very cheap to have them and maintain them, because the only costs were cheap clothes and rice. Besides, in the Jesuit residences, the titles of captivity were examined carefully by two or three Fathers deputed by the Provincial for this purpose. The menial jobs were considered as below dignity for the whites. Those with illegal or uncertain title were freed and their service was paid for. Those who had already served for some years were also granted their letter of manumission.24

Alessandro Valignano the visitor of the Jesuit missions noted in 1576 that many slave masters had donated slaves to the Jesuit residences. He feared that many of such slaves were illegally captured. He wished that slaves of all Jesuit residences in the Portuguese empire ought to be set free, as it had been done in the Jesuit province of Sicily. The authorities in India had replied that it was difficult to function in India without slaves and as to the title of slavery and good treatment, this had been ensured. The Jesuit lay brothers could not do in India the type of work they were doing in Europe. It was stated that in this country no one served another, except the slaves and some native boys.25

Valignano instructed ‘The Father of Christians’ (a State appointed official usually a priest to look after the protection and welfare of converts to Christianity) in September 1595 to look after the manumission of the slaves, particularly of those owned by the Portuguese, who tended to offer more resistance. In case they failed to yield to appeals to conscience, the cases were to be entrusted to the lay attorney of the Christians.26 It is mentioned that even the Fathers of Christians were accomplices in accepting declarations during baptism to cover the intentions of the slave buyers who claimed that the young slaves would be a burden to their parents who would kill them, or that they would be captured by pirates. The law mentioned that baptism had become a door to slavery, instead of being a door to freedom.27

THE THIRD PROVINCIAL COUNCIL OF GOA
IN 1585 AND DISCUSSION ON THE
FREEDOM OF SLAVES

The third provincial council was held in Goa in 1585 and discussion on slavery took place. It repeated the decree 13 of the First Council and decree 8 of the Second Council extending the freedom of slaves belonging to non-Christians including those in Melaka. It also repeated the prohibition of Muslims taking slaves through the Portuguese territories. A fine of 50 pardaus and excommunication was imposed upon the Captains and ship masters who permitted embarkation of such slaves without the knowledge of the Viceroy or the Prelate. They should force the masters to sell their slaves to Christians, or failing Christian buyers to non-Christians of the Portuguese jurisdiction.28

The decree 30 of the Third Council referred to the practice of some slave owners giving Christian names to their slaves without baptizing them. The masters were obliged to baptize a slave within six months after acquisition or within a month if the slave was 10 years of age or less. There was a fine imposed upon the defaulters.29

The decree 2 of the Third Council in 1585 ordered the slave masters to redeem within one year any of their slaves who might have been captured in wars or any such conflicts. The Council considered it to be their duty of gratitude and also defence of faith. If they were not redeemed within this period and succeeded in escaping from captivity they should be considered free. There was an annexe to the proceedings of this Council and it quoted from the Justinian code stating that Christian captives of Jews, gentiles or heretics in India, could not be considered legitimate slaves, even if any of their masters might later accept Christianity.30

THE FIFTH PROVINCIAL COUNCIL OF GOA
IN 1606: DISCUSSION ON THE SLAVE
MARRIAGES, SLAVES WITH LEGAL
CERTIFICATES AND FREEING

The Fifth Council repeated a decree of the Fourth about masters not impeding the marriage of their slaves and to sell them when married to freed slaves giving an impression that these could accompany them wherever they might have to go. Such sales should be restricted to the coast extending from the port of Diu in Gujarat to Kanyakumari region and not beyond. The council banned female slaves of less than 50 years of age from selling foodstuffs or do sewing work on the streets. The masters who permitted this should pay a fine of 20 pardaus for each breach of this order.31

The decree 15 of the fourth session of the fifth provincial council lamented that despite many bans and decrees of the past councils, the captivity of slaves and their abusive exploitation had been on the rise and there appeared to be no way of checking it. The council therefore authorized the Bishops in their respective jurisdictions to keep a watch on the ports where slave trafficking took place, deputing virtuous and responsible persons to examine the titles of captivity and hand these in writing to the respective slaves. They should also issue the certificates of legal possession to the respective slave masters. Any slave who was not thus examined and without such certificate should be considered freed.32

THE VARIOUS TYPES OF ILL-TREATMENT
OF SLAVES RECORDED IN THE
COUNCILS OF GOA

The Council held in Goa had noted the various types of ill-treatment meted out to slaves. A decree of the council in its fourth session referred to cruel treatment meted out to slaves by some masters to the point of killing some slaves. The council prohibited the practice of punishments with fire or cane and invited denunciation by those who might come to know of such punishments being practised. It prohibited forcing the slaves to work on Sundays and religious days of obligation or making them pay for things they lost or happened to break at home. The masters were advised to treat their sick slaves well and to advise them to frequent the sacraments.33

In 1606 the Council had noted the various other types of ill-treatment meted out to slaves and it included slaves punished cruelly with hot irons, leather straps, by pouring hot liquids, by pressing any part of their body with weights, by throwing pepper, oil, vinegar or salt into their eyes, by breaking their teeth or by whipping them repeatedly. The Council banned the said ill-treatments and said that any one violating this order should pay a fine of 50 pardaus. The Council decreed that sick slaves abandoned by their masters and living on streets and in hospital of the poor should be considered free if their masters did not take them back.34

PORTUGUESE PRIVATE TRADERS AND
SLAVE TRADE FROM NAGAPATTINAM
TO MELAKA, 1616-1625

Pedro Chirino, the Jesuit reported that the male and female slaves were brought by the Portuguese from Nagapattinam to Melaka. The women slaves were great seamstresses, cooks and very orderly and clean in their service.35

A Portuguese private merchant had declared in 1616 that he had transported four slaves namely Augustine, Adriana, Maria and Jacinto from Nagapattinam and Tuticorin (besides Catalina, Antonio and Pascual the three slaves from Sri Lanka) to Melaka.36 Evidences make it clear that the Portuguese missionaries on the Tamil Coast were willing to provide the necessary paperwork to turn an illegal purchase of a slave into a long-term labour or permanent slave contract. A common line of reasoning that developed by 1616 in Tamil country was that a person was a slave if he or she had been labelled by the Roman church council. Francisco Macedo a Portuguese slave merchant in 1620 justified his property rights over slaves in 1620 and referred to the provisions contained in the provincial councils of Goa. He claimed that the Hindus and Muslims in India were declared slaves because they were enemies of Christians.37

There are numerous references to Portuguese slaves who continued to be transported overseas from Nagapattinam. In a letter of 24 October 1625 the Dutch factor of Coromandel had mentioned that he had captured two ships of the Portuguese sailing from Nagapattinam to Melaka which had 300 slaves.38

PORTUGUESE SLAVE TRADE FROM NAGAPATTINAM
TO ACEH IN SUMATRA, 1621

Slave trade began to develop from Nagapattinam to Aceh. People were sometimes kidnapped and sold as slaves. Augustin de Beaulieu, a traveller reported that he met a few slaves of Nagapattinam brought to Aceh. These slaves had requested him on 2 March 1621 to rescue them from their owners by paying money. He however could rescue only four Christian slaves who were former residents of Nagapattinam. The santa casa da misericordia (The Holy House of Mercy) of Nagapattinam paid him 400 reals towards the expenses met by him on this count. Augustin de Beaulieu had sought the help of Kunkazhali Marakkayar of Tamil Coast who was at Aceh on 23 March 1621 and he helped him to carry out this mission of rescue of slaves with success.39

To conclude it may be said that the Portuguese officials and missionaries discussed about the nature of slavery and slaves. Portuguese private traders from Goa and Cochin came to the Tamil Coast and purchased salves. Tamil slaves were also exported from Nagapattinam to Melaka and Aceh in South East Asia. The missionary accounts provide a graphic description of the Portuguese private traders and their excess, including their active involvement in slave trade.

NOTES

1. Marco Polo, Travels of Sir Marco Polo, 2 vols., tr., Yule, London, 1903, p. 115; S. Jeyaseela Stephen, ‘Slavery and Society: Experience of the Dutch and the French Trading Companies in Coastal Andhra, AD 1600-1800’, in Social Evils in Andhra Desa, 17th & 18th Centuries, ed. R. Soma Reddy, M. Radhakishna Sarma and A. Satyanaryana, Hyderabad, 1999, pp. 75-96, see p. 76.

2. M.L. Dames, ed., The Book of Duarte Barbosa, 2nd edition, Hakluyt Society, London, 1921 p. 147; S. Jeyaseela Stephen, Portuguese in the Tamil Coast: Historical Explorations in Commerce and Culture, 1507-1749, Pondicherry, 1998, pp. 155-8.

3. Letter of Lourenço Moreno and Diogo Pereira to the king dated 20 December 1510 in Raymundo Antonio de Bulhao Pato, ed., Cartas de Afonso de Albuquerque, Typographia da Academia Real das Sciencias de Lisboa, 1903, tomo III, p. 317.

4. Joaquim Heliodoro da Cunha Rivara, Archivo Portuguez Oriental (hereafter APO-CR), 6 fasc. in 10 vols., New Delhi, Asian Educational Services, 1992, Fasc. 5, p. 1, pp. 52-3.

5. APO-CR, Fasc. 5, pp. 153-4.

6. APO-CR, Fasc. 5, parte I, p. 311.

7. APO-CR, Fasc. 5, p. 320.

8. António da Silva Rêgo, Documentação para a história das Missões do Padroado Português do Oriente, Lisboa, Agência Geral das Colónias, 1947-58, vol. X, p. 443.

9. APO-CR, Fasc. 5, parte I, p. 374.

10. Jose Wicki, ed., O Livro do Pai dos Cristãos, Lisboa, Centro de Estudos Históricos Ultramarinos, 1969, pp. 235-6.

11. Jose Wicki, Documenta Indica (hereafter DI), 18 vols., Roma, 1949-88, vol. V, Document 97, p. 665; S. Jeyaseela Stephen, ‘Economic Change, Institutional Development and Urbanization in Santhome, 1507–1676’, in Portuguese Presence in India During the Sixteenth and Seventeenth Centuries, ed. Yogesh Sharma and Jose Leal Ferreira, Delhi, 2008, p. 7.

12. Lúcio de Sousa, ‘Slave Networks and their Expansion through Macao to Europe and America’, Revista de Cultura, no. 35, July 2010, pp. 84-94, see p. 89.

13. Ibid.

14. DI, vol. I, p. 65, Letter of Miguel Vaz to Dom João III in Portugal in 1545.

15. DI, vol. I, pp. 297-8. Letter of Henrique Henriques to Igantius Loyola from Vembar on 31 October 1548.

16. DI, vol. X, pp. 125-9. Letter of Nicolao Lancillotto from Kollam to Ignatius Loyola in December 1550.

17. DI, vol. X, pp. 129-30.

18. Ibid.

19. Monumenta Ignatiana, Series Prima, Tomus Quartus, Madrid, Gabriel Lopez del Horno, 1906, ep. 2371, pp. 116-19.

20. Public Library of Évora, Portugal, O Primeiro Concilio Prouinçial çelebrado em Goa, no anno de 1567, Goa, João de Endem, 1568.

21. António da Silva Rêgo. Documentação para, vol. X, p. 343.

22. APO-CR, IV & V (II), p. 178.

23. DI, vol. VIII, p. 409.

24. DI, vol. X, pp. 214-15, 266.

25. DI, vol. X, pp. 638-9.

26. DI, vol. XVII, p. 88.

27. DI, vol. X, pp. 361-3.

28. APO-CR, pp. 135-7.

29. APO-CR, pp. 142-3.

30. APO-CR, pp. 177-8, 183-4.

31. APO-CR, p. 267.

32. APO-CR, pp. 267-8.

33. APO-CR, p. 51.

34. APO-CR, pp. 269-70.

35. Pedro Chirino, Relación De Las Islas Filipinas, Manila, Historical Conservation Society, 1969, pp. 141-2.

36. Archivo General de la Nación (hereafter AGN), Mexico City, Seccion Historia, 406, fls.187r-191v (1616).

37. AGN, Seccion Jesuitas, 4-26.2 (1620).

38. W. Ph. Coolhas, ed., Generale Missiven van de Gouverneurs-Generaal en Raden Aan Heren XVII der Verenigde Oostindische Compagnie, 9 vols., ’S Gravenhage, 1960-84, vol. I, p. 175, see also, p. 791.

39. Denys Lombard, Memoires d’un Voyage aux Indes Orientales; Un Marchand Normand a Sumatra, Paris, 1996, pp. 120-30.